Now, what we're going to go through next
is specifically for students at my school
who use, who are take, take the different
chemistry courses where we give them a
handout to be able to explain how this
handout works so you can better be able
to name and understand the different ions.
Let's take a look.
So this What this part of this video is
for is to help you get an introduction
on how to use the green sheet for
chem either chem 3a or chem 1a.
Now for the sheet usually it's
the color green, but right now
I have just the regular normal
version that we have as a pdf.
Um, how does this thing work?
It, it looks very, very complicated and
can be a little confusing if you are
just looking at it for the first time.
The one thing is, is I put
start here because that's
where you're going to start.
Now, one thing you might notice
is that it's in the shape of
something we covered in previous
videos, which is the T4 3 method.
Right, so it is in the exact same shape.
So what do I mean there?
Well, if you notice we have borate,
nitrate, and then silicate, right?
That was blue.
So that's our T.
Then for the other, for the next
column with phosphate and arsenate
and sulfate and all these guys, This
is our 4, so you can kind of roughly
see my really bad drawing of a 4 here.
And then chlorate is in the shape of a 3.
So we have each of those different
parts of the T4 3 method.
Now depending on which section
you are in, you might be
given this on your first test.
But if you know how to use it and
memorize it, then it'll make you faster
rather than trying to search every
little detail because if you only have
like an hour to take a test, You don't
want to be spending two to three minutes
trying to search all your references.
You want to be quick.
We start here.
The polyatomics, this is
all your major -ate endings.
So from here, the rest of the
sheet goes with our modifiers.
Okay, so the next two different,
uh, little tables here I refer
to as a modifier, meaning if
something does not quite match.
So the first portion here, this
column, and the naming rules, this
is all about if oxygens are changing.
So if you have more oxygens, less
oxygens, it's all about how are
those different oxygens differing.
So when we say we're starting, right,
we have our, uh, our 8 ending, and you
can see that, like, is kind of like
the first place most people will look
at, which is one less than the eights.
Um, if you have per, that means that
you have one more than the eights.
Hypo is one less, so it's a modifier.
So if your oxygens do not match,
you want to look at this table
for when the oxygens do not match.
Now what about the other ones?
Well, sometimes you might
have a hydrogen that could be
part of your species as well.
So that is a different kind of modifier.
So if you have a hydrogen species that
is on there, this is something that's
very common in buffers and in biology.
So if you're someone who has to
take Any of those things, which
buffers will be covered at, generally
around acid base chemistry, um, or
if you have to take higher order
chemistries, you will see that as well.
Now, the only way the hydrogen works
is based on the number of them, uh,
essentially it alters the charge, okay?
So the charge changes.
Now for every single H plus you add, it's
going to offer offset the charge by one.
So if I kind of zoom in here and
we notice, okay, we have phosphate,
which has a negative three charge.
Now if I add a single hydrogen here, we'll
notice how the charge is now negative two.
So if we add one H, that all of a
sudden changes that entire charge.
Now, what about two hydrogens?
Well, once again, you can see that, oh,
if I do two, now it's even more different.
It's now negative one.
So every time you add a hydrogen, it
offsets that charge by one, two, or
three, or four, or however many you add.
Right?
It's offering, it's offsetting the charge.
Now the naming changes too.
As you can notice when you add a hydrogen,
we just say the word hydrogen in front.
If we have two of them, it's dihydrogen.
Um, there's also other terminology too.
Um, one of the other ones that's common
in biology is saying the word bi or B I.
for a hydrogen.
So it's hydrogen, let's say, or let's
say if you have sodium biphosphate
or sodium hydrogen phosphate.
So these are different ways for
you to be able to understand that.
Now the other part is this part I
call like your alternate starts.
I don't really have a better way of
writing that, but alternate meaning
like if something doesn't match the H
and you can't seem to figure out its
charge and it doesn't match anything,
this is where this guy comes in.
It's essentially like.
all the leftovers that
are not as important.
Now keep in mind this is not every single
polyatomic that you ever will come across,
but this is generally the majority of
the major ones that you'll see either in
lab or in your in textbooks or in class.
So there could be others that you've
come across and you have to kind of,
you know, do some little research
and see exactly what it is and how to
name it, how to be familiar with it.
But this is the general idea of
one, how to use the T4 3 method
and how to use your green sheet.
I hope that this video helped you.
Thank you so much for listening
and please come back for more.
All right.
See y'all later.
Bye now.